They would call the order of the regular meeting of the Miami City Council for September 20, 2021.
Two, proclamation for recognition of Osborne drugs on its Osborne drugs incorporated on its 50th anniversary.
So we got a proclamation here for Bill.
You bet. So we want to thank you guys 50 years in business of Miami as huge.
I don't think we have very many of those.
So that's a testament to you and your family for the many years that you guys have dedicated to our community.
You guys have a celebration.
Friday, dinner clock.
Yeah.
Yeah. That's pretty amazing.
That's pretty amazing for you guys to be open 50 years and for her to be there 49.
Yeah.
That's pretty cool.
Thank you.
Three public input.
Let's get the answers.
We have none.
Four.
Concentrate agenda.
Staff recommends we approve item.
Item five.
Do eight.
We have any questions about those.
Oh, I see Mike and Marsher both here.
If we have any questions.
I'll second.
Nine.
Approve or reject.
Title six.
Civil rights non-discrimination program.
Going to log in.
Bit more.
I can get you started on this.
This is a program that the federal government initiated two or three years ago.
Now days in order to get federal grants.
You have to have a non-discrimination policy and program in place.
So right now we're waiting on the latest round of COVID money.
The ARPA money, which we cannot get until we have this in place.
Any grant that comes through.
Department of Homeland Security.
You have to have this policy in place.
Basically, we've taken their suggested framework.
We've made a few adaptations to fit our needs.
Once this is approved, we.
we can post it on our website and it can be translated into 11 different languages, which is part
of what the feds want to see. I don't know what else do we need to add to it.
Any other entity that we give money to such as we have our outside organizations which would include
the senior citizens, the crisis center, on and on. Those entities also have to have a similar
non-discrimination policy for us to be able to continue to pass money through to them even though
it's not necessarily federal money, the feds are still requiring us to be able to continue to get
any federal money. I'll make a motion we've brewed. We've got to have those grants.
All right. Thank you, good. 10, or 2021, that's your 419 section 6-3.1 international property
maintenance inspection program. Kristen McLean. Yes, how are you? So we've both implemented. It starts today.
Since that pace meeting, if you had anybody contact you, I'd ask any questions.
Not one person.
It's a ban of you got any calls or anything about it.
I have not heard from anybody, and most particularly none of you in regards to this.
I was going to ask that up in the Councilman.
I don't receive anything calls about it.
So, like you did a good job with me.
The only thing I heard at that pace meeting that really rang a bell, and I don't know if it's been implemented or not,
but it will be.
But I believe Mr. Damron brought up the auto, auto pace,
and I think there was some consensus amongst us just visiting at that meeting that they should be allowed to do that.
As long as we could get in there on some basic schedule that makes sense to protect our citizens.
And it looks like it might save us some stress and take good care of our people.
I'm making motion, we approve.
Thank you.
I understand.
Number 11, approve, waving annexation proceedings
before the city's owning and planning commission
for the annexation of a parcel known as the Dollar General
Store at the South East corner of Highway 125
in the East Street, Southwest, and consent
of the Schedule of Public Hearing at a future city council meeting.
This about is back at the beginning of this year,
we, the city agreed to some concessions
that enabled the Dollar General Store to be built,
and in return they were going to agree
to that property being annexed into the city
once the store was up and running.
And this is something that we've been a little bit slow
on getting to, but it needs to be done.
It's been brought to our attention
that it's being sold from the developer to the corporation
or a franchisee.
And so we really need to get on the stick and get this moving.
Our procedures, as set out in our ordinances,
call for the entire matter to go through the planning and zoning
commission before it comes back to the city council.
In this particular instance, because of the timeframes
that we're dealing with here, we're asking the, you wave that.
The proceedings before the planning and zoning commission.
There is nothing in the state statutes that require that.
That's just the way that we have done it
through our policies and such.
So in order to move this thing along as expeditiously as we can,
we're asking to wave the hearing before the planning
and zoning commission and to have this set
for a public meeting, public hearing in front of this board,
which is required by the state statutes.
And then just proceed on with getting the annexation done
as quickly as we can.
And it will take out another meeting in another couple of weeks of the process to get it done.
You'll still have the final say so on it.
I'll make a motion.
Aye.
Thank you.
12.
Concentrate the agenda.
Staff recommends we approve items A through G.
So moved.
13.
Another new business to the committee that is risen since posting this agenda.
14.
Staff reports.
15.
Mayor and council community announcements.
It is.
I've been in several booster club meetings over the last two or three weeks.
It is kind of an exciting time.
And my amathletics, you don't know where it goes or how long it's maintained.
But the football team won it's first two games since 2005.
The first two games are the seasons since 2005.
And Tom coming Friday night in a game taken competing.
Softball.
It's more personal and pertinent to all of my daughters.
But they will play tomorrow evening in a really really really really significant district game
against Skytook.
And they're playing well enough to give themselves an opportunity in the next couple days.
And then in the next few days, to solidify a spot to host a regional for a spot in the state
tournament.
So, my I'm a school's athletics and the attendance and the mojo that goes with that for
the community is on an uptick and I just wanted to call that out.
And tomorrow night, those sophomore girls play at home.
We are at home.
We start at five o'clock.
So, I think you're sweating everybody to be there that can be there.
Come on.
Well, pork nachos, sidewalks.
Anybody else?
All right, city manager communications.
Mr. Mayor, so tonight, really quick, I just wanted to give an update.
In clarifying the information that you may have heard around the ARPA funding in the
cities, in any funds that the city may receive.
So, this latest round is what you're reading.
Consider the ARPA funding, the city will receive about 2.3 million.
We have not received any of that money yet.
Ben alluded to that earlier that we're still completing the application as most cities are.
And, you know, just as a quick break down, the state is a hole is going to get about 3.2 billion with a B.
The state itself will be managing about 1.9 of that through the issue through grants.
And, use by the state as a whole.
And then county and local governments will split 1.3 billion.
About 770 million of that is being distributed to the 777 counties.
10 municipalities that are larger than 50,000 will be sharing 315 million.
And my amma is what is considered a non-intitled entity or unit.
Or any U, non-intitlement unit, which is local government less than 50,000 citizens will be sharing about 240 million across the UUs.
And so, their constitutes the 3.2 million that we are likely to receive.
It will come in two installments.
We'll get 2.3.
It's actually 2.285 to be exact.
That money will receive half of that.
Pretty shortly after we complete the application and in the other half and about 12 months.
And the guidance that's coming out of the Oklahoma Municipal League and from the state,
because the state will be receiving the any use money in distributing that where the larger cities and the counties get it directly,
which is why some of them may have already received their funding.
They're getting it directly from the federal government.
The state is receiving the any use money in distributing it.
to the any use.
So that being said, the guidance that's coming from the state,
who's distributing it, and the OML, who is partnering with the state in this distribution,
is just highly recommending that cities and municipalities, counties and everyone, you know,
washes, don't get into a big of a rush, that we have until December 31st of 2024
to pretty much encumber the funds towards a project, and we haven't, until December 31st,
2026 to spend the money, and although I don't think we set on the money until 2026,
what we do need to do is really work together, come up with a priority of project that we really
consider deeply how these will impact the city and our citizens as a whole. I think we need to be
taking these projects and the list of priorities and consulting with our county partners, with our
tribal partners, and with our state partners. We look for opportunities for overlap where we can work
together to achieve even larger outcomes with these these monies. And certainly look for opportunities
where there's grant funding that we could take advantage of whereby maybe this money is simply used as
matching funds. So the opportunity to utilize this 2.285 million and maybe be able to stretch that out
into a much greater impact to the community as a whole, if we're mindful and take our time and
really consider the projects that are going to make a difference. These are really one-time funds,
so these are funds that because they're not guaranteed in future years, you've got to be very careful
about what you expend them on, you don't want to go purchase something that is going to have multiple
future years of maintenance costs or upkeep or refresh and not have the money to do that in future
years. So one-time costs are things, you know, infrastructure, capital improvement, things like that.
And since they're really stressing that these are really once in a generation type funds that the state is
receiving that if we all work together, we can really do some massive things with it. So I just wanted to
pass along that information, make sure that everybody understood and then, you know, our recommendation
is that we'd be very mindful of how we spend this money and watch closely because the guidance, although
it's very restrictive at this time, what we can spend the money on, it's very likely that those rules could
change as we go down the road and they can open it up to a broader spectrum of opportunities. So we want to
be mindful of that as well, but happy day.
answer any questions anybody may have. I know that's been a lot of talk about it and a lot of news
in the paper talking about it so I wanted to make sure we clarify anything tonight.
Okay. All right. Well that was my primary update tonight. So thank you all.
All right, Ben. No, we're back now. I have to say anything other than go to vote.
Okay. All the players back into the city council meeting and we're going to vote on a few things discussed
in council meeting. Great. And we're going to vote on a the 18 A claim by Ray Neal.
It seeks compensation for property damage and the emotion to either deny the claim or approve the claim.
I make a motion we reject the claim. And then see. That's it. So we're done. We're done here.
So 21 adjournment. All right. Now we'll be back in regular session on the MSUA.
And we're now to 15 ratified GRDA legal claims. This would be the claims that we tabled from last
meeting and we're looking for approval to pay or denial to not pay and 16 adjournment.
Bye.